<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>org.develz.Crawl.desktop</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-2.0</project_license>
  <name>Dungeon Crawl Stone Soup</name>
  <summary>Roguelike dungeon exploration game</summary>
  <developer id="org.develz.crawl">
    <name>The Dungeon Crawl Stone Soup Devteam</name>
  </developer>
  <description>
    <p>
      Crawl is a fun game in the grand tradition of similar games like Rogue,
      Hack and Moria. The objective is to travel deep into a subterranean cave
      complex and retrieve the Orb of Zot, guarded by many horrible and hideous
      creatures.
    </p>
    <p>
      If you have never played Crawl (or a similar game) before, select the
      tutorial from the starting menu. The tutorial explains the interface in
      five easy lessons. Once you're familiar with the controls, you may want to
      play a few games using hints mode.
    </p>
    <p>
      This is the Stone Soup version of Dungeon Crawl.
    </p>
  </description>
  <categories>
    <category>Game</category>
  </categories>
  <url type="homepage">https://crawl.develz.org/</url>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">org.develz.Crawl.desktop</launchable>
  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <caption>The Dungeon</caption>
      <image type="source">https://crawl.develz.org/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/musu.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Sigmund the Dreaded</caption>
      <image type="source">https://crawl.develz.org/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/meph.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>
  <update_contact>guillaumepoiriermorency@gmail.com</update_contact>
  <releases>
    <release version="0.33.0" date="2025-05-02">
      <description>
        <p>
          We are pleased to announce the release of Dungeon Crawl Stone Soup: 0.33 “Reforge Yourself”!
        </p>
        <p>
          DCSS 0.33 features a new magic school, two new playable species, twelve new talisman items,
          a new portal level, and many new and revamped monsters!
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>New magic school + background: Forgewrights, building explosive constructs.</li>
          <li>Two new species: Poltergeists and Revenants.</li>
          <li>Twelve new talismans have been added, and Shapeshifters have been reworked.</li>
          <li>Ghost vaults are moved into a game-long repeating portal, the Necropolis.</li>
          <li>Yet more new monsters, decorations, and traps spread throughout the Dungeon.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.32.1" date="2024-09-25">
      <description>
        <p>
          Bugfix release.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Fix blockable beam attacks from monster spells being blocked 100% of the time.</li>
          <li>40 other bug fixes, interface improvements, and documentation updates.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.32.0" date="2024-08-29">
      <description>
        <p>
          We are pleased to announce the release of Dungeon Crawl: Stone Soup 0.32 “Gods and Makers”!
        </p>
        <p>
          DCSS 0.32 features redesigns of four gods, two new playable species, eleven new spells, many
          new and revamped monsters, as well as new decorations throughout the Dungeon!
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Beogh, Dithmenos, Yredelemnul, and Makhleb have been substantially revamped.</li>
          <li>Since everybody can become orcs, reworked Mountain Dwarves replace Hill Orcs.</li>
          <li>New species: Coglins, dual-wielding gizmo-inventing goblins in exosuits.</li>
          <li>More new spells, aimed at new school combinations and higher levels.</li>
          <li>Many more new and revamped monsters and decorations throughout the Dungeon.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.31.0" date="2024-01-19">
      <description>
        <p>
          We are pleased to announce the release of Dungeon Crawl: Stone Soup 0.31 “The Alchemy of Forms”!
        </p>
        <p>
          DCSS 0.31 features some major spell school and starting background changes, a variety of new
          spells, many dangerous new monsters, and some major species changes.
        </p>
        <p>
          The Transmutations forms spells have been moved into talisman items, which allow permanently
          shifting into forms based on the new Shapeshifting skill. The remaining Transmutations spells
          and the Poison Magic spells have been merged into a new Alchemy school. The Shapeshifter and
          Alchemist starting backgrounds replace Transmuter and Venom Mage, respectively. To support
          these changes, this release adds 4 new spells, sees 7 spells reworked into improved
          replacements, and has many tweaks to the levels and schools.
        </p>
        <p>
          The new Oni species replaces Ogres. Oni love a good drunken brawl, gaining double effect when
          drinking any potion that restore HP or MP, and also perform an immediate cleaving melee attack.
          They are otherwise similar to Ogres, but also have horns and some increased apts. Starting at
          XL 7, Armataurs now regenerate HP and MP while rampaging. They also lose their double potion
          effect, and no longer read scrolls slowly. Felids now have an extra life at XL 1 and don’t lose
          XLs when dying. Tengu have an inherent acrobat effect (like the amulet) at XL 1, and gain 4 EV
          at XL 7 instead of gaining an EV bonus and fast movement. Humans gain the exploration healing
          effect formerly found on Meteorans, which are no more. Instead, players of any species can now
          rush to find gems stashed at the end of many branches as achievement items.
        </p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.30.1" date="2023-06-30">
      <description>
        <p>
          Bugfix release.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Fix zooming on local tiles</li>
          <li>Many other bug and documentation fixes</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.30.0" date="2023-05-05">
      <description>
        <p>
          We are pleased to announce the release of Dungeon Crawl: Stone Soup 0.30 “The Reavers Return”!
        </p>
        <p>
          DCSS 0.30 features the return of the legendary Reaver background. These warrior-mages start
          with two new powerful yet situational spells: Kiss of Death and Momentum Strike. They also
          start with the Hailstorm spell, which has been moved down to level 3 yet can sometimes miss.
        </p>
        <p>
          The new Armataur species replaces Palentongas, who have rolled peacefully off into the sunset.
          Armataurs are large, scaly mammals that wear bardings, but instead of rolling and curling,
          they have innate rampage and a long tongue mutation that doubles potion effects and slows down
          scroll reading.
        </p>
        <p>
          A grand total of 7 new spells have been added! Two we’ve already mentioned for Reaver, with
          two more being likewise new designs and three replacing existing spells:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            Kiss of Death (L1 Conj/Necro): does high draining damage to an adjacent enemy, at the cost
            of significant max HP drain to the caster.
          </li>
          <li>
            Momentum Strike (L2 Conj/Tloc). Redirects the caster’s momentum for a damaging attack that
            doesn’t require line of fire, but locks the caster in place for some turns after a hit (and
            cannot be recast until this expires).
          </li>
          <li>
            Cigotuvi’s Dreadful Rot (L2 Necro/Air/Pois). Rots away the caster’s flesh to create a cloud
            of deadly miasma on their tile. Replaces Corpse Rot.
          </li>
          <li>
            Volatile Blastmotes (L3 Fire/Tloc). Creates an explosive cloud on the caster’s tile, usable
            as a land mine or tricky tool. Replaces Conjure Flame.
          </li>
          <li>
            Vhi’s Electric Charge (L3 Tloc/Air). Launches the caster at a nearby foe and launches a
            crackling melee attack, phasing through creatures en route.
          </li>
          <li>
            Arcjolt (L5 Air/Conj). Electrocutes everything adjacent to the caster, everything adjacent
            to those creatures, etc, etc, in a chain. Replaces Lightning Bolt.
          </li>
          <li>
            Plasma Beam (L6 Fire/Air): Fires a bolt of lightning and another bolt of fire, both at the
            most distant foe.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          We’ve added 6 new unrands and made changes to 11 existing ones. Additionally you can now find
          randart orbs, scarves, and magical staves!
        </p>
        <p>
          Finally, Lugonu has been mutated into a new form. Banishment is available at 2* piety (instead
          of 3*) and mutates foes that resist getting banished. To encourage adventurers to abandon
          their current god, Lugonu helpfully banishes some hostile monsters whenever other gods act
          with their wrath. There are also now more Lugonu altars in the Abyss, and more piety is
          awarded for conversions in the Abyss.
        </p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.29.1" date="2022-09-11">
      <description>
        <p>
          Quick bugfix release after the tournament.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>20+ bug and documentation fixes</li>
          <li>Improvements to linux packaging support infrastructure</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.29.0" date="2022-08-25">
      <description>
        <p>
          We are pleased to announce the release of Dungeon Crawl: Stone Soup 0.29 “Shooting Stars”!
        </p>
        <p>
          DCSS 0.29 features a sweeping rework of Necromancy, streamlining and upgrading many of its spells, 
          along with similar improvements to the necromantic god Kikubaaqudgha. 
          Ranged weapons have likewise been streamlined and reworked to be more satisfying to use.
        </p>
        <p>
          For those seeking a special challenge, we’ve also added a new Meteoran species that heals when 
          seeing new terrain and has great skills and attributes. However, Meteorans have to move fast, 
          with only one-tenth the normal time per floor before they suffer heavy draining.
        </p>
        <p>
          Many backgrounds now start with extra scrolls, potions, or other consumables, allowing more tactical 
          options when faced with a sticky situation. Speaking of sticky situations, characters cast into 
          the Abyss will find that monsters there once again give experience and piety, and an ultra-dangerous 
          ‘deep abyss’ is now accessible…
        </p>
        <p>
          Many new item types have been added, like scrolls of poison and wands of quicksilver. 
          Some of these ‘alternate’, with only one type of item from a set being generated in any given game. 
          We’ve also added many exciting new unique monsters, from Amaemon the Diabolical Poisoner to the alt-timeline 
          troll Parghit the Mighty.
        </p>
        <p>
          Launchers, long blades and short blades all now use dexterity instead of strength when calculating damage,
          allowing new evasive playstyles. Monsters no longer gain and lose ‘random energy’, and can instead
          launch opportunistic attacks on fleeing players. As always, there are many more changes small and large alike!
        </p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.28.0" date="2022-02-04">
      <description>
        <p>
          We are pleased to announce the release of Dungeon Crawl: Stone Soup 0.28
          “The Rise and Fall of Ignis Zotdust and the Spiders from Hell”!
        </p>
        <p>
          DCSS 0.28 features a new Cinder Acolyte zealot background that begins
          the game worshiping a new god, Ignis, the Dying Flame. Cinder Acolytes
          start with the new Scorch spell, a -1 flaming branded weapon of choice,
          and five stars of piety. Ignis worshipers cannot gain piety, losing it
          only when using Ignis’ abilities. The abilities are Fiery Armour, which
          grants AC and retaliation flame damage, Foxfire Swarm, which summons
          many foxfires, and Rising Flame, a one-time ability sends the player one
          level above. Once all piety is spent, players will typically abandon for
          another god, and Ignis dies forever when wrath is over.
        </p>
        <p>
          The Hell branches have been revised to offer substantially more
          challenge. Each branch features a distinct and persistent negative
          effects that applies while in the branch along with timed effects common
          to all Hells. The branches all have revised monster set with many new
          monsters and smaller layouts for the first six levels, each of which has
          only one downward staircase. The Spider branch has likewise been
          retooled with a roster of new creepy-crawlies, new and revised end maps,
          and updates to the existing layouts and vaults.
        </p>
        <p>
          A new magical orb item type exists for the shield slot. Each orb type
          grants an ego with a powerful passive effect, such as a 3-radius halo
          or a reduction of monster willpower at the expense of your own. The
          god Yredelemnul has been completely redesigned, granting passive
          reaping and accepting the reaped zombies as payment for its dark
          abilities. Okawaru and Jiyva have also seen significant, though not
          quite as sweeping, changes.
        </p>
        <p>
          A batch of new spells have been added, As always, there are dozens of
          new deadly vaults, and many more changes small and large alike!
        </p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.27.1" date="2021-08-21">
      <description>
        <p>
          We’ve uploaded the 0.27.1 bugfix release. Packages for Windows, MacOs,
          and Linux are all available on the download page. Thanks to all the many
          contributors who helped with this release, including patches and bug
          reports!
        </p>
        <p>Highlights:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The frequency of D:1 jackals is reduced.</li>
          <li>Sigmund and Robin are nerfed gently.</li>
          <li>Maxwell’s Capacitative Coupling now has LOS range.</li>
          <li>80 other fixes, tweaks, copy-edits, and interface improvements.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.27.0" date="2021-07-30">
      <description>
        <p>
          We are pleased to announce the release of Dungeon Crawl: Stone Soup
          0.27 “The Cursed Flame”!
        </p>
        <p>
          DCSS 0.27 features a new Djinni species that cast spells using HP, can
          only learn new spells at random as they level up, and only use the
          spellcasting skill to train magic. We’ve redesigned Ashenzari, who now
          offers curses for your gear to gain piety and skill levels, at the
          cost of destroying the item when the curse is removed.
        </p>
        <p>
          A batch of new spells have been added, including Manifold Assault,
          which attacks multiple foes at once with your melee, Storm Form, which
          transforms you into a tempest with electrified, cleaving melee and the
          ability to hurl yourself as lightning at foes, and Animate Armour,
          which draws out the spirit of your armor to fight by your side. Polar
          Vortex is a more damaging, ice-themed replacement for Tornado.
          Maxwell’s Capacitive Coupling is a level 8 air-themed replacement for
          Absolute Zero that vaporizes a nearby monster after a delay. Chain
          Lightning has been reworked into a more powerful level 9 spell.
        </p>
        <p>
          Spell books have many new types and generate more often, but contain
          fewer spells. We’ve re-balanced branch monster sets and end maps, as
          well as made new end maps for Lair, Shoals, and Snake. As always,
          there are dozens of new deadly vaults, and many more changes small and
          large alike!
        </p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.26.1" date="2021-02-05"/>
    <release version="0.25.1" date="2020-07-17"/>
    <release version="0.24.0" date="2019-10-25"/>
    <release version="0.21.1" date="2018-02-03">
      <description>
        <p>Major bugfixes and updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Dith shadow mimic of launcher attacks no longer copies the enchant and ego of the launcher.</li>
          <li>Monsters lose constriction by Borgnjor's Vile Clutch when they are moved by any means.</li>
          <li>Formicids can now manually cancel Dig status, allowing them to use Wu Jian's Wall Jump ability after digging.</li>
          <li>Wu Jian's Wall Jump ability now works under silence.</li>
          <li>New splash screen art by froggy.</li>
          <li>Numlock on Windows systems no longer causes unpredictable repeating movement.</li>
          <li>Alt-F4 no longer causes freezing in Tiles on Windows systems.</li>
          <li>Resizing the local Tiles window during prompts no longer causes crashes.</li>
          <li>SDL 2 contrib updated to 2.0.7, which fixes compilation under Msys2.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          Dith shadow mimics of launcher attacks were giving you all free
          enchantment and ego damage. That's simply unfair to those poor
          dungeon monsters, so we had to fix it! The numlock key causing
          repeating movement was reported by users far and wide, so many thanks
          to advil for tracking down and fixing that rather difficult bug.
          Hopefully you enjoy the new splash art by South Korean artist froggy,
          whose inspirational depiction of Boris and Natasha is a personal
          favorite.
        </p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.21.0" date="2018-01-06">
      <description>
        We're pleased to announce the release of Dungeon Crawl Stone Soup 0.21:
        "Gnoll Country for Old Jian"! 0.21 features a new species, a new god, a
        new spell, and many significant updates and general improvements to the
        game.
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.0">
    <content_attribute id="violence-cartoon">mild</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="violence-fantasy">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="violence-realistic">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="violence-bloodshed">mild</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="violence-sexual">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="drugs-alcohol">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="drugs-narcotics">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="drugs-tobacco">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="sex-nudity">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="sex-themes">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="language-profanity">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="language-humor">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="language-discrimination">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="social-chat">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="social-info">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="social-audio">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="social-location">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="social-contacts">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="money-purchasing">none</content_attribute>
    <content_attribute id="money-gambling">none</content_attribute>
  </content_rating>
</component>
